So-a!
So-a!
My Lord!
Tuanku!
Sit here.
Duduklah di sini.
Wake up already.
Bangunlah.
-Why are you here? -I'm off today.
- Kenapa kau di sini? - Aku libur hari ini.
I've been following you guys all day because I was curious.
Aku mengikuti kalian seharian karena penasaran.
Why did you fight, by the way?
Kenapa bertengkar?
Hey.
Hei.
Are you not going to thank me?
Kau tak bilang terima kasih?
Fine, let's call it even.
Baiklah, kita impas.
She's so shy.
Dia sangat pemalu.
What are you so worried about?
Apa yang kau khawatirkan?
It's nothing.
Tidak ada.
You look like you had a near-death experience just now.
Kau seperti baru mengalami pengalaman nyaris mati.
The customer before you said he almost died four times this month.
Pelanggan sebelum kau bilang dia hampir mati empat kali bulan ini.
-Four times? -Yes.
- Empat kali? - Ya.
In the end,
Pada akhirnya...
If it's really his fate, I guess he could think like that.
Jika itu memang takdirnya, kurasa dia bisa berpikir begitu.
You don't seem to understand what fate is.
Tampaknya kau tak paham itu takdir.
Sorry?
Apa?
Half of your fate, which has to do with the length of your life, is unchangeable.
Separuh dari takdir yang berkaitan dengan umurmu tak bisa diubah.
That's a given.
Itu sudah digariskan.
But the other half is different.
Tapi sisanya berbeda.
Depending on how one deals with their fate, it's changeable.
Tergantung cara orang menangani nasibnya, itu bisa berubah.
So what I'm saying is that it is possible
Jadi maksudku sangat mungkin untuk mengubah takdir.
It's the same with driving a taxi. Depending on the driver's skills,
Seperti mengendarai taksi. Tergantung kemahiran supir,
your trip can be fast, slow,
perjalananmu bisa cepat, lambat, nyaman,
comfortable, or uncomfortable.
atau tidak nyaman.
At times, you can't get to your destination.
Terkadang, kau tak sampai ke tujuanmu.
Today, you met a good driver.
Hari ini, kau bertemu pengemudi yang baik.
Your trip will be fast and safe.
Perjalananmu akan cepat dan aman.
Why are you laughing?
Kenapa tertawa?
It feels like I've been watching a romantic comedy all day.
Rasanya seperti menonton film komedi romantis seharian.
It's not my favorite genre, though.
Bukan genre favoritku.
A romantic comedy? What do you mean?
Komedi romantis? Apa maksudmu?
You even had a fight at the end. It's perfect.
Kalian bahkan bertengkar di akhir. Sempurna.
So, why did you fight?
Kenapa bertengkar?
WHITE LOTUS HOUSE
RUMAH TERATAI PUTIH
Ms. Yun.
Nona Yun.
Something came up.
Sesuatu terjadi.
It's become a bit crumpled, but you can still sign it.
Ini agak kusut, tapi kau masih bisa menandatanganinya.
Is something wrong?
Ada apa?
No.
Tidak.
Let's sign it.
Mari tanda tangani.
Right now.
Sekarang.
Is someone against selling the land?
Ada yang menentang penjualan tanah?
No. Not at all.
Tidak. Tidak sama sekali.
Keep this. I'll send you a new one.
Simpanlah.
-Let's just-- -We can't today.
- Biarkan saja... - Tak bisa hari ini.
I need the company's seal.
Aku butuh stempel perusahaan.
I was in such a hurry. I didn't think about that.
Aku terburu-buru. Tidak terpikir olehku.
I'm sorry.
Maafkan aku.
Goodbye.
Sampai jumpa.
Are you kidding me?
Apa kau bercanda?
Sorry?
Apa?
You came all the way here.
Kau jauh-jauh ke sini.
Do you think I'll let you go like this?
Kau pikir akan kubiarkan kau pergi?
Oh, my goodness!
Astaga.
Are you okay?
Kau baik-baik saja?
When your head is a mess, physical labor is the cure.
Saat pikiranmu kacau, pekerjaan fisik adalah obatnya.
You're right.
Kau benar.
You seemed like a heartless person.
Kau tampak seperti orang yang tak berperasaan.
I didn't know you had a hobby like this.
Aku tak tahu kau punya hobi seperti ini.
That's prejudice.
Itu prasangka.
A heartless person can love trees too.
Orang yang tak berperasaan bisa mencintai pohon juga.
Also, I have a healthy and pumping heart.
Aku juga punya hati
In any case, you do seem like a cold person.
Bagaimanapun, kau memang tampak dingin.
I wonder how you became a successful businessperson.
Aku penasaran bagaimana kau bisa jadi pebisnis sukses.
I can read people's emotions if I want to.
Aku bisa baca perasaan orang jika mau.
I just try not to.
Aku berusaha tak melakukannya.
I see. Do you have supernatural powers or something?
Begitu. Kau punya kekuatan gaib atau semacamnya?
-Isn't it amazing? -Sadly, not really.
- Bukankah itu luar biasa? - Tidak juga.
There are many people like you around me.
Ada banyak orang sepertimu di sekitarku.
I know a person who can teleport,
Aku tahu seseorang yang bisa berteleportasi,
a person who can make diamonds endlessly,
yang bisa membuat berlian tanpa henti,
and a person who can master anything just by seeing it once.
dan yang bisa menguasai apa pun hanya dengan sekali melihatnya.
That person can transform as well.
Orang itu bisa berubah bentuk juga.
-They're dangerous. -Right?
- Mereka berbahaya. - Benarkah?
Give it to me.
Berikan padaku.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Of all hobbies, why do you like to take care of trees?
Dari semua hobi, kenapa suka mengurus pohon?
Trees live longer than me.
Pohon hidup lebih lama dariku.
Trees create a forest, but they don't try to control it.
Pohon menciptakan hutan, tapi tak mengendalikannya.
From grasses and insects to winds,
Dari rumput dan serangga ke angin,
they embrace everything.
pohon menyambut semuanya.
They live with other beings.
Pohon hidup bersama makhluk lain.
They offer things to others to prove their existence.
Menawarkan sesuatu pada yang lain untuk membuktikan keberadaanya.
I was right, wasn't I?
Benar, 'kan?
When you're exhausted, you forget everything.
Saat lelah, kau lupa segalanya.
What was it?
Ada apa?
This is strange.
Ini aneh.
-Why do I want to tell you everything? -It's because I'm a stranger.
Kenapa aku ingin cerita?
A stranger?
Orang asing?
If you just talk to yourself, it won't get you anywhere.
Jika kau bicara sendiri, masalah tak akan selesai.
This is strange.
Ini aneh.
It shouldn't make sense, but it does.
Itu tak masuk akal, tapi benar.
Just imagine you're talking to a tree.
Bayangkan kau bicara pada pohon.
I just...
Aku hanya
made a common mistake that everyone makes.
membuat kesalahan yang dibuat semua orang.
I relied on someone without realizing it.
Aku mengandalkan seseorang tanpa menyadarinya.
I started to have expectations.
Aku mulai punya harapan.
Most of all, I revealed my feelings, which was the worst of it all.
Terlebih, aku menyatakan perasaanku, dan itu yang terburuk.
You probably thought you could do that with that person.
Mungkin kau pikir kau bisa begitu.
No.
Tidak.
I shouldn't have.
Seharusnya tidak.
He's going to leave anyway.
Lagi pula dia akan pergi.
To be precise, he's not a person.
Lebih tepatnya, dia bukan manusia.
He's a bad person.
Dia orang jahat.
Sorry?
Apa?
He's going to leave anyway.
Dia juga akan pergi.
But he stirred your heart.
Tapi dia mempermainkan hatimu.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
The farm is always open.
Perkebunannya selalu terbuka.
It's always short of hands too.
Dan selalu kekurangan pekerja.
Mr. Shin.
Pak Shin.
I'd like to apologize for being prejudiced against you.
Aku minta maaf sudah berprasangka terhadapmu.
Oh, my.
Astaga.
Bye.
Sampai jumpa.
He is going to leave anyway.
Dia juga akan pergi.
But he stirred your heart.
Tapi dia mempermainkan hatimu.
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa di sini?
I was thinking about how I can get my power back.
Aku memikirkan cara mendapatkan kekuatanku kembali.
Let's go.
Ayo.
Did you go to see the land?
Kau pergi melihat tanahnya?
No.
Tidak.
Why not?
Kenapa?
You acted as if you had to go there immediately.
Kau bertingkah terburu-buru ke sana.
I don't have a driver's license, you know.
Aku tak punya SIM, 'kan?
Bin has one. You should've asked him to take you.
Bin punya. Harusnya kau memintanya mengantarmu.
I told you that I can't trust him.
Aku tak memercayainya.
Then are we good now?
Kita sudah berbaikan sekarang?
Are you still mad at me?
Kau masih marah padaku?
-I said I'd protect you because-- -I lied to you.
- Kubilang akan melindungimu karena... - Aku bohong padamu.
What I told you earlier in the day was all a lie.
Yang kukatakan sebelumnya
Humans are like that.
Manusia memang seperti itu.
When people are angry, they spew out whatever comes to mind.
Saat marah, mereka bilang apa pun yang muncul di pikiran.
I didn't mean it, so please don't take it to heart.
Aku tak bermaksud begitu, tolong jangan diambil hati.
I was just rambling on, so you shouldn't take it seriously.
Aku hanya mengoceh, jadi jangan menganggapnya serius.
Don't worry.
Jangan cemas.
I knew.
Aku tahu.
When you lie, it's so obvious.
Saat kau bohong, itu terlihat jelas.
Where are you?
Di mana kau?
-I'm working. -Where are you now?
- Bekerja. - Di mana kau sekarang?
I'll kill you if you show up here.
Akan kubunuh kau jika ke sini.
I'm the only one who has it tough.
Hanya aku yang memilikinya.
Those in the Land of Earth seem to be doing fine even without Judong.
Para penghuni Negeri Tanah baik-baik saja tanpa Judong.
And you don't even get in trouble for slacking all the time.
Kau bahkan tak mendapat masalah karena bermalas-malasan.
I have problems too.
Aku juga punya masalah.
Water is the worst.
Negeri Air yang terburuk.
It's still like this even after I tried to resuscitate it.
Masih seperti ini bahkan setelah kucoba menolongnya.
Soon, a day will come when we'd have no choice but to give up.
Kelak, akan tiba waktunya saat kita harus menyerah.
We can't bring the dead back to life.
Kita tak bisa menghidupkan orang mati.
Guess what I did all day.
Tebak yang kulakukan seharian.
Do you actually think I'd be curious?
Kau pikir aku penasaran?
I followed Habaek around all day and...
Aku mengikuti Habaek seharian dan…
Don't make me explode in jealousy.
Jangan buat cemburuku meledak.
Just do your work.
Kerjakan tugasmu.
I saw Jugeollin.
Aku lihat Jugeollin.
Coming and going like the wind is my specialty.
Datang dan pergi seperti angin adalah keahlianku.
What happened? Has Habaek found out everything?
Apa yang terjadi? Habaek tahu semuanya?
I'm asking if he knows everything now.
Apa dia tahu semuanya sekarang?
Did Jugeollin tell him everything?
Jugeollin memberi tahu semuanya?
Jugeollin is really something.
Jugeollin itu lain dari yang lain.
He ran away like a nimble rat.
Dia kabur seperti tikus.
Just find Judong as soon as possible.
Cari Judong secepatnya.
We should send him back soon. It's really stressing me out.
Kita harus kirim dia kembali. Membuatku stres.
Then why are you looking for an apartment?
Kenapa mencari apartemen?
Aren't you planning to live with him?
Kau tak mau tinggal dengannya?
I hope you find a nice place.
Kuharap kau temukan tempat bagus.
It doesn't look like Habaek wants to go back soon anyway.
Sepertinya Habaek tak mau kembali secepatnya.
What? Why not?
Apa?
All right, let's start with breathing.
Baik, kita mulai dengan bernapas.
Breathe in through your nose...
Tarik napas lewat hidung...
and breathe out.
dan embuskan.
Now, you're going to use your right hand and left leg.
Sekarang, gunakan tangan kanan dan kaki kiri.
Put them over your left hand and left foot, then twist.
Letakkan di atas tangan dan kaki kiri, lalu putar.
Your palms must touch each other.
Telapak tangan harus saling menyentuh.
Then breathe in and out. Like this.
Tarik napas yang dalam dan embuskan. Seperti ini.
Oh, no, Ja-ya. Try to stay balanced.
Oh, tidak. Ja-ya. Cobalah tetap seimbang.
Bend down more.
Lebih rendah lagi.
Keep going.
Teruskan.
Now, release. That's it.
Sekarang, lepaskan. Selesai.
A morning live show approached us saying that they want to use
Program siaran langsung pagi menghubungi, katanya mu pakai
the outdoor space at our resort for their main segment.
area luar di resor kita untuk segmen utamanya.
They'd need the space for two hours
Mereka butuh selama dua jam dari pukul 06.00 hingga 08.00.
What do those in the marketing team think?
Apa kata tim pemasaran?
They said that it won't really help us promote our resort,
Mereka bilang itu tak begitu membatu mempromosikan resor kita,
but they'll probably use Ms. Shin to persuade us again.
tapi mungkin Bu Shin akan membujuk kita.
Even yesterday, I was bombarded with interview requests for you.
Kemarin, aku kebanjiran permintaan wawancara untukmu.
Thanks for your hard work.
Kuhargai kerja kerasmu.
How about the proposal for the summer event?
Lalu soal proposal acara musim panas?
I haven't received it. Please check on it for me.
- Belum kuterima. Periksa saja untukku. - Baik.
One more thing. On my computer,
Satu lagi. Di komputerku,
you'll find documents from Culture Space.
ada dokumen dari Ruang Budaya.
-Please email them to me. -Sure.
- Kirim ke poselku. - Baik.
CEO SHIN HU-YE
CEO SHIN HU-YE
Hey!
Hei!
-Mr. Min, where's Mr. Shin? -He stepped out for a meeting.
- Pak Min, di mana Pak Shin? - Keluar untuk rapat.
Why is he always so busy?
Kenapa dia sibuk terus?
If this is about the interview, I thought I'd made it clear.
Jika soal wawancara, kukira sudah kujelaskan.
I know. You heartless people.
Aku tahu. Dasar tak berperasaan.
Forget about it. By the way,
Lupakan.
why did Mr. Shin smirk at me earlier?
kenapa Pak Shin tersenyum padaku tadi?
-He smirked? -Yes, he did.
- Dia tersenyum? - Ya, benar.
-Do you know why? -I can't read his mind,
- Kau tahu kenapa? - Aku tak bisa membaca pikirannya,
but I would've laughed because you looked funny.
- tapi aku tertawa kau tampak konyol. - Apa?
You were twisting your body.
Kau memelintir tubuhmu.
Anyone would've laughed as it looked so funny.
Siapa pun akan tertawa.
-Hey, how dare you-- -Call me Mr. Min.
- Beraninya kau... - Panggil aku Pak Min.
Hey, stop!
Hei, berhenti!
Did I really look funny?
Apa aku tampak konyol?
That's not good.
Itu tidak bagus.
MR. SHIN HU-YE
TN. SHIN HU-YE
Hello?
Halo?
Oh, no.
Oh, tidak.
Did I call too early?
Teleponku terlalu pagi?
No.
Tidak.
I have all paperwork ready. Shall I schedule the meeting for Monday?
Semua berkas sudah siap.
Sure, that would be great.
- Tentu saja. - Begini saja...
-Pardon? -Who knows what else will happen?
Apa?
Let's just get it done. I'll bring my company's seal.
Mari selesaikan. Kubawa stempel perusahaanku.
Sure.
Tentu.
I'll see you later, then.
Sampai jumpa nanti.
I have to stop by the farm in the afternoon.
Aku harus mampir ke perkebunan sore ini.
A rare flower seedling I ordered has arrived.
Bibit bunga langka yang kupesan tiba.
I see. Then I'll see you in the evening.
Baiklah. Sampai jumpa nanti malam.
Why are you so excited? Who is it?
Kenapa gembira sekali?
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa di sini?
How did you even get in here?
Bagaimana kau bisa masuk?
My keys!
Kunciku.
You're unbelievable.
Kau keterlaluan, ya.
-It was left in the door lock. -What?
- Ini tergantung di pintu. - Apa?
The fact that I left it there
Fakta bahwa aku meninggalkannya
and how you trespassed into my place are two different things.
dan kau menyelonong masuk adalah dua hal yang berbeda.
This is my place. What is the problem?
Ini rumahku. Apa masalahnya?
I've told you so many times, yet you still don't get it.
Sudah kuberi tahu berkali-kali, tapi kau masih belum paham.
Are you trying to sell the land because of money?
Kau mencoba menjual tanah demi uang?
Because you need money?
Kau butuh uang?
That's right. I wouldn't sell it if the situation wasn't so bad.
Benar.
-Sorry? -Didn't you say
- Apa? - Bukankah katamu
having a lot of money will make you happy?
uang membuatmu bahagia?
Do as you wish.
Lakukan sesukamu.
By the way, whom were you on the phone with just now?
Omong-omong...
You were smiling like an idiot.
Kau tersenyum seperti orang bodoh.
You don't need to know.
Kau tak perlu tahu.
-What? -It was a guy, wasn't it?
- Apa? - Seorang pria, 'kan?
-What did you say? -It must've been a guy.
- Apa katamu? - Pasti seorang pria.
Your face has turned beet red,
Wajahmu berubah merah,
and your heart is skipping beats.
jantungmu berdetak kencang.
You're breathing heavily.
Napasmu berat.
Your eyes are shaking.
Matamu gemetar.
It was a man. You talked to a man.
Pasti pria. Kau bicara dengan seorang pria.
It's just like in the movies.
Seperti di film-film.
What? What did he say?
Apa? Apa katanya?
-What should we do? -What do you mean?
- Kita harus bagaimana? - Apa maksudmu?
We can take a taxi if there's no bus.
Kita naik taksi jika tak ada bus.
Not that.
Bukan itu.
Us.
Kita.
Where did you go in the middle of the movie?
Ke mana kau pergi di tengah film?
Shall we burn everything?
Apa kita bakar saja?
I probably have similar taste to you.
Selera kita mungkin sama.
I can't stand romantic comedies.
Aku tak tahan komedi romantis.
I just saw something unbearable in real life.
Baru kulihat hal mengerikan di dunia nyata.
Where is my fruit drink?
Mana minuman buahku?
I didn't-- Oh, gosh.
Tidak... Astaga.
Lady Mura sent them because she didn't like Lord Habaek's clothes.
Nona Mura yang mengirimnya karena dia tak suka pakaian Tn. Habaek.
I didn't talk to a guy.
Aku tak bicara dengan pria.
Was it a girl?
Wanita?
It was a guy,
Memang pria,
but I didn't blush because I talked to a guy.
tapi aku tak tersipu karena berbicara dengannya.
He's just...
Dia hanya...
Forget it.
Lupakan saja.
It doesn't matter.
Itu tak penting.
Let's just say so.
Begitulah.
So did she talk to a guy or not?
Jadi dia bicara dengan pria atau tidak?
She did.
Ya.
Is it important?
Apa itu penting?
Why did I try to explain myself?
Kenapa aku harus cerita panjang lebar?
What's the big deal?
Apa masalahnya?
I almost told him he wants to buy the land.
Hampir kubilang dia mau membeli tanahnya.
You may sell everything else,
Kau boleh jual yang lain,
but not the land.
tapi bukan tanahnya.
Then do whatever you want.
Terserah kau saja.
Why does he keep changing his mind?
Kenapa dia terus berubah pikiran?
It's so confusing.
Sangat membingungkan.
Didn't you say that having a lot of money will make you happy?
Bukankah kau bilang punya banyak uang membuatmu bahagia?
Does he...
Apa dia
want me to be happy? No way.
mau aku bahagia? Tak mungkin.
He's testing me. He's so sly.
Dia mengujiku. Dia begitu licik.
-You're here. -Who were they?
- Kau di sini. - Siapa mereka?
On your land,
Di tanahmu,
Korean leopards' feces were found.
kotoran macan tutul Korea ditemukan.
What was found?
Ditemukan apa?
Poop. Korean leopards' poop.
Kotoran macan tutul Korea.
And?
Lalu?
Korean leopards died out
Macan tutul Korea punah
during the Japanese colonial era and the Korean War.
saat era kolonial Jepang dan perang Korea.
The last one lived in Changgyeonggung,
Yang terakhir tinggal di Changgyeonggung,
and it died in 1973.
dan mati tahun 1973.
That was the end of Korean leopards.
Itulah akhir dari macan tutul Korea.
And?
Lalu?
The Korean Leopard Preservation Council is working with Russia
Dewan Pelestarian Macan Tutul Korea bekerja sama dengan Rusia
to resurrect Korean leopards.
untuk membangkitkan macan tutul Korea.
Luckily, they found their poop on your land.
Untungnya, mereka temukan kotoran mereka di tanahmu.
My goodness. And?
Astaga. Lalu?
They want you to keep the land until their research is finished.
Mereka mau kau pertahankan tanah itu sampai penelitian selesai.
They heard about it at the real estate agency.
Mereka dengar dari agensi lahan yasan.
Are you done?
Sudah selesai?
Get out.
Keluar.
Korean leopards should be brought back.
Macan tutul Korea harus dibangkitkan.
Sang-yu.
Sang-yu.
I don't think Korean leopards pooped only on my land.
Kupikir macan tutul Korea tak hanya buang air di tanahku.
Mr. Ma is coming with his father today, right?
Pak Ma dan ayahnya akan datang hari ini, 'kan?
He canceled the appointment, saying he was going on a trip.
Dia membatalkan janji temu karena dia melakukan perjalanan.
There are no other appointments scheduled today. Do you want to go home?
Tak ada jadwal lain hari ini.
You're closing down the clinic soon anyway.
Sebentar lagi klinik juga kau tutup.
Are you trying to be rebellious or funny?
Apa itu sindiran atau lelucon?
Goodbye,
Selamat tinggal,
my sweet drunk.
cinta sesaatku.
Don't come to me again.
Jangan datang lagi.
Don't ask the forest for direction.
Jangan tanyakan arah pada hutan.
Don't send your regards with the wind.
Jangan titip salammu pada angin.
You were...
Kaulah...
my everything. I'll remember you forever.
segalanya bagiku. Akan kuingat kau selamanya.
Breathe.
Bernapaslah.
My goodness!
Astaga.
What is this?
Ada apa ini?
How many times has it happened?
Berapa kali itu terjadi?
How can the king of romance pass out before a kissing scene?
Bagaimana bisa raja romansa pingsan sebelum adegan ciuman?
It's not like Hye-ra will eat him.
Hye-ra pun tak akan memakannya.
I know.
Aku tahu.
Is Hye-ra overpowering?
Apa Hye-ra begitu mengintimidasi?
Can't he tell charismatic from overpowering?
Dia tak tahu beda berkarisma dan menakutkan?
She's just charismatic.
Dia berkarisma.
Male actors keep passing out.
Aktor prianya terus pingsan.
Hye-ra is not a bad actress.
Hye-ra bukan aktris yang buruk.
-But they say she can't do romance. -They say she's stiff.
- Tapi katanya dia tak bisa adegan roman. - Katanya dia kaku.
They say there is no chemistry between her and her partner.
Katanya tak rasa antara dia dan pasangannya.
They say she eats her partners.
Katanya dia memakan rekannya.
Mr. Kim.
Pak Kim.
-Yes? -What about my apartment?
- Ya. - Bagaimana apartemenku?
Are you looking?
Sudah kau cari?
Of course, I'm looking for a place for you.
Tentu saja, aku mencari tempat untukmu.
You said it has to be a penthouse with a view
Kau bilang griya tawang dengan pemandangan
and furniture that suits your taste.
dan perabotan yang cocok dengan seleramu.
Can you elaborate a little more?
Bisakah kau ceritakan lagi?
You don't understand?
Kau tak mengerti?
Why don't you understand?
Kenapa kau tak mengerti?
Your lips.
Bibirmu.
Let me put some lipstick on you. Something with more color.
Biar kupakaikan lipstik.
Go have some steaks.
Pergilah makan steik.
I hired a chef with three Michelin stars.
Kusewa koki dari restoran tiga bintang Michelin.
You're here.
Kau di sini.
Give that to me and go have your steaks.
Berikan padaku dan makan steikmu.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
You'll soon be only shooting movies like Amazons.
Kau hanya akan syuting film seperti Amazons nanti.
Hye-ra.
Hye-ra.
You look so pretty.
Kau terlihat sangat cantik.
By the way, the shooting is over.
Omong-omong, syutingnya sudah selesai.
The actor was sent to the hospital.
Aktornya dikirim ke RS.
-Do you want to have a drink? -I'm meeting someone.
- Kau mau minum? - Aku ada janji.
Don't worry about him.
Jangan cemaskan dia.
He has nothing else to do. He follows me everywhere.
Tak ada yang bisa dilakukan. Dia mengikutiku ke mana-mana.
You have a good friend.
Kau punya teman yang baik.
Our friendship is stronger than anything in the world.
Persahabatan kami lebih kuat dari apa pun di dunia.
Friendship so strong that it can even cut through steel.
Persahabatan yang sangat kuat hingga bisa menembus baja.
A friend who you could even die for.
Kau bahkan rela mati untuk teman seperti itu.
How can you find a friend like that?
Bagaimana bisa menemukan teman seperti itu?
After going through all kinds of things, you become good friends.
Setelah melalui banyak hal, kau akan jadi teman yang baik.
I'm looking for a place to stay.
Aku mencari tempat tinggal.
I see. Thanks to your long stay,
Begitu. Karena kau menginap lama,
our resort has become famous.
resor kami menjadi terkenal.
I'm sorry it's so sudden.
Maaf mendadak.
Our marketing team will have to work hard from now on.
Tim pemasaran kami akan kerja keras mulai kini.
I'm surprised someone can have a normal conversation with you.
Aku terkejut seseorang bisa mengobrol normal denganmu.
I'm surprised you said you were sorry too.
Aku terkejut kau bisa minta maaf juga.
He's a nice guy.
Dia pria yang baik.
He is strong to the strong and weak to the weak.
Dia kuat pada yang kuat, lemah pada yang lemah.
What?
Apa?
I didn't know you had standards like that.
Aku tak tahu kau punya standar seperti itu.
You know nothing about me.
Kau tak tahu apa pun soal aku.
HABAEK
HABAEK
Habaek.
Habaek.
I'll be right there. Get ready.
Aku segera ke sana. Bersiaplah.
Biryeom?
Biryeom?
Don't tell him yet.
Jangan katakan padanya.
He's not trustworthy.
Dia tak bisa dipercaya.
See you soon.
Sampai jumpa.
Why don't you tell Ms. Descendant?
Kenapa tak beri tahu Nn. Keturunan?
It's our problem.
Ini urusan kita.
I don't want to drag her into it.
Aku tak mau menyeretnya.
What was the conversation about?
Apa yang kalian bicarakan?
Is it something only gods from the Land of Water should know?
Apa hanya dewa Negeri Air yang boleh tahu?
I feel left out.
Aku merasa ditinggalkan.
You should go now.
Pergilah.
Look.
Dengar.
If you keep doing this, I might turn into a bad guy.
Jika terus begini, aku akan jadi orang jahat.
Whatever.
Terserah.
Fine.
Baiklah.
What should I do to make her want to be with me?
Apa yang harus kulakukan agar dia mau bersamaku?
Should I bring that punk to her?
Haruskah kubawa bajingan itu padanya?
I'm so hungry.
Aku lapar sekali.
Where am I supposed to go if I can't settle into even the human world?
Ke mana aku harus pergi jika susah menetap di dunia manusia?
Gosh, I'm starving!
Astaga, aku lapar.
PEOPLE WHO ARE CALLED DEITIES
ORANG-ORANG YANG DISEBUT DEWA
ANNOUNCEMENT: OUR REGULAR BREAKFAST GET-TOGETHER WILL BE HELD
PENGUMUMAN: SARAPAN BERSAMA AKAN DIADAKAN
This is my first time back here since that day.
Ini kali pertama aku ke sini lagi.
Why are we here?
Kenapa kita di sini?
Too much time has passed for us to find any traces.
Sudah terlalu lama jedanya untuk kita bisa menemukan jejak.
Did you say Judong asked you to come here that day because something seemed odd?
Kau bilang Judong
Yes.
Ya.
It's not that way. He went the other way to pick up the sacred stone.
Bukan ke sana. Dia ambil batu keramatnya ke arah lain.
What's the matter?
Ada apa?
What?
Apa?
What is that?
Apa itu?
I didn't think much of it when I first saw it here,
Saat kutemukan di sini, aku tak peduli,
but what Judong said bothers me.
tapi kata-kata Judong mengusikku.
-What does this look like to you? -This... This is...
Menurutmu apa?
Blood.
Darah.
But...
Tapi...
I do feel the energy of human blood,
Aku merasakan energi darah manusia,
but that's impossible.
tapi itu mustahil.
Nothing of humans can leave traces on this land.
Tak ada manusia yang bisa meninggalkan jejak di tanah ini.
I know. It purifies itself of all human traces.
Aku tahu.
If it's not from the human world,
Jika bukan dari alam manusia,
could it be from someone from the divine realm?
mungkinkah ini milik penghuni kayangan?
Those from our realm can leave traces here,
Dewa-dewi bisa tinggalkan jejak,
but none of us has blood.
tapi tak satu pun dari kita punya darah.
Then what on earth...
Lantas...
is this?
apa ini?
We did it!
Kita berhasil!
Is it done?
Sudah selesai?
Don't move your hand.
Jangan bergerak.
There we go.
Begini.
Is it done now?
Sudah selesai?
It's done.
Selesai.
We're finished!
Kita sudah selesai.
Gosh, my back hurts.
Astaga, punggungku sakit.
Thanks to you, I could get it done quickly.
Berkat dirimu, semua cepat selesai.
Grandma said you should join us for noodles
Kata nenek mampirlah ikut kami makan mi
if you're hungry.
jika kau lapar.
You guys are having noodles today.
Kalian makan mi hari ini.
I'm so sorry.
Maaf sekali.
I have to get going now because I have an important appointment.
Aku harus pergi karena ada pertemuan penting.
I see. That's like a promise.
Aku mengerti. Seperti janji.
It's important to keep promises. You should get going, then.
Penting untuk menepati janji. Pergilah.
Thank you for understanding.
Terima kasih pengertiannya.
Hold on a second.
Tunggu dulu.
Mr. Shin!
Pak Shin!
Is there a bug on my arm? Is it a worm?
Apa ada serangga di tanganku? Apa itu ulat?
What kind of bug was it?
Serangga jenis apa itu?
It had many legs. It made my skin sting.
Kakinya banyak. Itu menyengat kulitku.
You're okay now. Don't cry.
Kau sudah tak apa-apa. Jangan menangis.
Don't cry, okay? All is well now.
Jangan menangis, ya? Sudah tak apa.
It's okay. Stop crying. There.
Tak apa-apa. Berhenti menangis.
Let's go, okay?
Ayo pergi, ya?
Yes, Ms. Yun.
Ya, Nona Yun.
Do you think it's related to Judong's disappearance?
Menurutmu ada kaitannya dengan hilangnya Judong?
It does seem odd.
Itu memang aneh.
The lowly deities might know more about this than we do.
Dewa rendahan mungkin lebih paham soal hal macam ini.
-Will you keep this from Biryeom? -Don't tell him yet.
- Rahasiakan dari Biryeom, ya? - Jangan cerita dulu.
I don't like that punk either.
Aku benci si berengsek itu.
He came up with the idea of divine servants just to hurt you.
Dia beride soal pelayan surgawi itu hanya untuk melukaimu.
I don't even want to see him when I think about that.
Aku bahkan tak mau melihatnya saat teringat.
I don't know why he got so nosy and meddled like that back then.
Aku tak tahu kenapa dia penasaran tadi.
By the way,
Omong-omong,
you do want to find Judong soon, right?
kau ingin segera temukan Judong, 'kan?
-What? -Biryeom said something strange.
- Apa? - Biryeom mengatakan hal aneh.
He told me that you probably don't want to go back soon.
Dia bilang kau mungkin tak mau kembali.
What did he mean by that?
Maksudnya?
Biryeom... was talking nonsense, right?
Biryeom...
"I'd rather keep my mouth shut if I have to lie."
"Lebih baik tutup mulut ketimbang harus berbohong."
That's you, Habaek.
Itu katamu, Habaek.
You must know.
Kau pasti tahu.
I lie to you often.
Aku sering berbohong kepadamu.
You've never lied to me, though.
Tapi, kau tak pernah bohong padaku.
Habaek,
Habaek...
do you know this?
Tahukah kau?
Do you know why?
Tahu kenapa?
It's because you're well aware of the weight words carry.
Karena kau selalu hati-hati saat berbicara.
Once you utter something, you do your best to keep your word.
Saat mengucap sesuatu, kau berupaya keras menepatinya.
That's why I'm saying this. Even if what Biryeom said is true,
Maka, inilah pesanku.
Mura.
Mura.
I don't want you to remember the despair and pain from the old days.
Aku tak mau kau ingat sakit dan kepedihan masa lalu.
Mura, what...
Mura, apa...
What are you talking about?
Apa maksudmu?
Did I jump to conclusions? I'll be relieved if it's not true.
Itu kesimpulanku. Aku lega jika itu tak benar.
With the dignity of the next king and the authority of the ruler,
Dengan martabat calon raja dan wewenang penguasa,
please punish me for my arrogance.
hukum aku atas kesombonganku.
I'll gladly accept it.
Aku akan menerimanya.
DECLARATION OF INTENT TO SELL REAL ESTATE PROPERTY
PERNYATAAN NIAT PENJUALAN LAHAN YASAN
Please stamp your seal.
Silakan bubuhkan.
Sure.
Tentu.
You may sell everything else, but not the land.
Kau boleh jual yang lain, tapi bukan tanahnya.
What's the matter? Is there something wrong?
Ada apa? Ada masalah?
No.
Tidak.
Then do whatever you want.
Terserah padamu.
Yes, he told me to do whatever I want.
Benar.
This deal is finally done.
Akhirnya bisa sepakat.
Do you know something, Ms. Yun?
Kau tahu ini, Nona Yun?
I somehow ended up overseeing this contract with you,
Malah aku yang akhirnya mengurusi kontrak denganmu,
and those in the department in charge think it's strange.
dan orang kantor pikir itu aneh.
If...
Kalau...
If there's any misunderstanding, I'll explain--
Jika ada salah paham, akan kujelas...
And there are also things you don't really need to explain.
Ada juga hal-hal yang tak perlu kau jelaskan.
Let's have dinner together to celebrate closing this deal.
Mari makan malam bersama untuk merayakan ini.
The land has been passed down in your family for generations.
Tanah itu diwariskan keluargamu secara turun-menurun.
Don't you feel a bit sad?
Kau tak merasa sedih?
It's a useless piece of land that hasn't done my family any good,
Itu tanah yang tak berguna bagi keluargaku,
so it's fine.
jadi tak apa-apa.
Your parents must be sad about it, though.
Orang tuamu pasti sedih.
I can't ask my father's opinion for a certain reason.
Aku tak bisa meminta pendapat ayahku karena suatu alasan.
As for my mom...
Dan ibuku...
My mom is dead, so I can't ask her opinion either.
Ibuku sudah meninggal, jadi aku tak bisa minta pendapatnya.
I'm so sorry. I assumed that--
Maafkan. Aku berasumsi bahwa...
I know, right?
Aku tahu 'kan?
I guess that's why you can never assume anything about anyone.
Itu sebabnya jangan berasumsi.
You look like you were born with a silver spoon in your mouth,
Kau tampak seperti orang yang terlahir bergelimang harta,
but it's probably not the case. I have to be right about it.
tapi mungkin tidak demikian. Apa aku benar?
Yes, you're right.
Ya, kau benar.
I'm an orphan.
Aku yatim piatu.
I don't know who my mother is,
Aku tak tahu siapa ibuku,
and my father abandoned me after abusing me.
ayahku meninggalkanku setelah menganiayaku.
Just leave it. I'll ask the waiter to bring a new one.
Biarkan saja.
Aren't you hungry? Do you want to eat? There are great restaurants in this area.
Kau tidak lapar?
-Yes. -I'm not hungry.
- Ya. - Aku tak lapar.
I said I'm not hungry.
Kubilang, aku tak lapar.
That woman over there. Don't we know her?
Wanita itu. Bukankah kita mengenalnya?
It's Ms. Descendant.
Itu Nn. Keturunan.
I think I've seen that guy somewhere.
Kurasa aku pernah melihat pria itu.
I'm sure that's Mr. Shin.
Aku yakin itu Tn. Shin.
Sorry?
Apa?
He's the CEO of the resort I model for.
Dia CEO dari resor di mana aku jadi model.
I didn't know those two knew each other.
Aku tak tahu mereka saling kenal.
Oh, right. It's that friend of hers who seemed rich.
Benar sekali. Itu dia temannya yang tampak kaya.
It's him.
Itu dia.
I didn't know he was a CEO.
Aku tak tahu dia CEO.
-I guess he really is rich. -Let's go.
- Ternyata dia memang kaya. - Ayo pergi.
Maybe... I shouldn't have said what I said earlier.
Mungkin...
I'm sorry for ruining the mood.
Maaf merusak suasana.
No, that's not it. I was just...
Tidak, bukan itu. Aku hanya...
I know what you're thinking.
Aku tahu pikiranmu.
You're viewing me from a doctor's point of view, aren't you?
Kau melihatku dari kacamata dokter, kan?
"It's weird that he's talking as if it's not a big deal."
"Aneh dia membicarakannya seolah-olah bukan masalah besar."
-No, that's not-- -"Does he have DID?
- Tidak, bukan... - "Apa dia punya GID?
Is he a psychopath? Could he have anger management problems?"
Dia psikopat? Mungkin punya masalah manajemen amarah?"
What are you saying? I never thought any of that.
Apa maksudmu? Aku tak pernah mengira itu.
Let's go. I'll drive you home.
Mari. Kuantar kau pulang.
I'll take the bus.
Aku naik bus saja.
The night breeze is nice. I want to walk a little.
Angin malamnya enak. Aku mau jalan kaki.
Okay.
Baiklah.
It's nice weather to take a walk.
Cuaca bagus untuk jalan-jalan.
Thank you for today.
Terima kasih untuk hari ini.
By the way,
Omong-omong...
I'm curious about something.
aku penasaran soal sesuatu.
I've been curious since yesterday.
Aku penasaran sejak kemarin.
Let me ask you, now that we're talking about the wind.
Pertanyaan saat kita bicara tentang angin.
How fast is the wind that shook your heart?
Seberapa cepat angin yang mengguncang hatimu?
-Mura. -Yes?
- Mura. - Ya?
Do you want the answer...
Kau mau jawaban
to the question you asked me earlier?
atas pertanyaan yang kau ajukan tadi?
Biryeom is wrong.
Biryeom salah.
Really?
Sungguh?
The truth isn't important.
Kebenaran itu tidak penting.
What's important is my answer.
Yang penting adalah jawabanku.
You're right.
Kau benar.
Your answer is what's important.
Jawabanmulah penting.
-Right? -Pardon?
- Benar, 'kan? - Apa?
How fast is the wind that shook your heart?
Seberapa cepat angin yang mengguncang hatimu?
I'd like to know if I'm capable of stopping that wind.
Aku ingin tahu apa aku mampu menghentikannya.
I don't think that wind means that much to me.
Kurasa angin itu tak berarti bagiku.
There's not much meaning in calculating its speed.
Tak penting menghitung kecepatannya.
I'll stop it with my own power if I want it to stop.
Aku akan menghentikannya dengan kekuatanku sendiri jika ingin.
I don't need anyone's help.
Aku tak butuh bantuan siapa pun.
And...
Dan...
it has already stopped.
angin itu sudah berhenti.
That's my answer...
Itu jawaban
to your question.
untuk pertanyaanmu.
Is he sleeping already?
Apa dia sudah tidur?
My gosh!
Astaga.
I noticed that...
Aku melihat...
all the lights were off, so I was wondering
semua lampu mati, jadi aku penasaran
if you still hadn't come home yet.
apa kau belum pulang.
-Today-- -Go inside. You must be tired.
- Hari ini... - Masuklah. Kau pasti lelah.
I'm also going to go inside soon.
Aku juga masuk sebentar lagi.
Okay.
Baiklah.
Yun So-a.
Yun So-a.
Come home early from now on.
Pulanglah lebih awal.
It's too late right now.
Ini terlalu larut.
And it's also too dark.
Dan terlalu gelap.
Okay.
Baiklah.
Well, you sometimes...
Terkadang kau
came out and stood by the streetlight
keluar dan berdiri di samping lampu jalan
and wondered how you can get your power back.
dan memikiran cara untuk mendapatkan kekuatanmu kembali.
I'm not doing that anymore.
Tak akan kulakukan lagi.
I'm going to return to the Land of Water anyway.
Lagi pula aku akan kembali ke Negeri Air.
Those from our realm can leave traces here,
Dewa-dewi bisa meninggalkan jejak di sini,
but none of us has blood.
tapi tak satu pun dari kita punya darah.
-Yes? -About the lowly deities...
- Ya? - Tentang dewa rendahan...
Do you know a lowly deity that knows everything,
Kau kenal dewa rendahan yang tahu banyak termasuk kisah zaman dulu?
I feel like...
Sepertinya aku...
I might know something about this blood.
tahu sesuatu tentang darah ini.
What's his problem?
Apa masalahnya?
He's so cold. Did he watch a movie that has a cold-blooded character in it?
Dia sangat dingin.
I'm not going to do that anymore.
Tak akan kulakukan lagi.
I'm going to return to the Land of Water anyway.
Lagi pula aku akan pulang.
I already know.
Aku sudah tahu.
He didn't need to tell me again.
Dia tak perlu memberitahuku lagi.
Did he find out that I sold the land?
Apa dia tahu aku menjual tanahnya?
Whatever. It's my land. I'll do whatever I want with it.
Terserah. Itu tanahku. Terserah mau kuapakan.
DECLARATION OF INTENT TO SELL
PERNYATAAN NIAT PENJUALAN
It's all over now.
Semua sudah berakhir.
I'm going to clear everything now.
Akan kubereskan semuanya sekarang.
I can't wait to go to Vanuatu.
Aku ingin ke Vanuatu.
You may sell everything else,
Kau boleh jual yang lain,
but not the land.
tapi jangan tanahnya.
You're not talking to me, are you?
Kau tak bicara kepadaku, 'kan?
What am I thinking right now?
Apa yang sedang kupikirkan?
Goodness!
Astaga.
Are you in there?
Kau di dalam?
I need to talk to you.
Aku mau bicara.
My gosh! You surprised me.
Astaga, kau mengejutkanku.
Why didn't you answer me?
Kenapa tak menjawabku?
-What do you want? -I have something to ask you.
- Apa maumu? - Aku mau bertanya sesuatu.
-It's for my mental health. -What is it?
- Untuk kesehatan mentalku. - Apa?
Why can't I sell that land?
Kenapa aku tak boleh jual tanah itu?
The gate will stay there even when the owner of the land changes.
Gerbangnya akan tetap ada bahkan jika ganti pemilik.
-That's right. -Then why can't I sell it?
- Benar. - Lalu kenapa tak boleh?
It's not like it will get blocked.
Gerbangnya juga tak terblokir.
It might be a bit uncomfortable,
Mungkin agak merepotkan,
but you guys have powers to overcome all that.
tapi kalian punya kekuatan untuk mengatasinya.
-That's why I told you to do as you wish. -I know, but I'd still like to know why.
Maka kubilang terserah.
They'll criticize me for not being able to protect that land.
Mereka akan mengkritikku karena tak bisa melindungi tanah itu.
But I thought none of that mattered because you're born to be the king anyway.
Kupikir semua itu tak penting
Yes, it doesn't matter.
Ya, itu tidak penting.
But even in our world, there are those who seek opportunity.
Tapi bahkan di alam kami, ada saja yang mencari peluang.
Does that answer your question?
Pertanyaanmu terjawab?
If it did, please leave.
Jika ya, pergilah.
Rest up.
Istirahatlah.
That's nothing compared to my situation.
Hal remeh dibandingkan situasiku.
And it's not like it'll happen for sure. It's just an assumption, isn't it?
Dan itu tak akan terjadi.
Asking me to give up my choice
Memintaku mengorbankan pilihan bukan hal yang pantas dilakukan dewa.
I'm good now. It's all clear.1
Selesai. Semua aman.
They'll criticize me...
Mereka akan mengkritikku
for not being able to protect that land.
karena tak bisa melindungi tanah itu.
SIMA QIAN, THE WAYS OF HUMANS
SIMA QIAN, JALAN MANUSIA
Bacteria is a living thing too. It's sad that we have to kill them under the sun.
Bakteri juga makhluk hidup.
What?
Apa?
Did you eat?
Kau sudah makan?
Do you want to eat together?
- Mau makan bersama? - Kami akan makan dengan Nn. Mura.
Really? That's good to hear.
Sungguh? Senang mendengarnya.
By the way, we saw you with the CEO of the resort yesterday.
Omong-omong, kami melihatmu bersama CEO resor kemarin.
-What? -That guy who looks rich.
- Apa? - Pria yang terlihat kaya.
You guys looked good together.
Kalian terlihat serasi.
Let's go.
Ayo pergi.
See you later.
Sampai nanti.
He saw me?
Dia melihatku?
Does that mean he knows I signed the contract?
Apa dia tahu aku tanda tangan kontrak?
How can he be sure that he's the one who is buying my land?
Kenapa dia yakin bahwa Pak Shin yang membeli tanahku?
Wait a minute.
Tunggu dulu.
He saw the contract.
Dia melihat kontraknya.
That means he knows, right?
Artinya dia tahu, 'kan?
No.
Tidak.
He already told me that he doesn't know anything.
Dia bilang tak tahu apa-apa.
Did he find out?
Apa dia sudah tahu?
Is that why he met with that goddess? Did they meet to plan...
Apa itu alasan dia bertemu dewi itu? Untuk merencanakan...
Whatever. So what if he knows?
Terserah. Lantas, kenapa kalau tahu?
He told me to do as I please.
Katanya terserah mauku.
My gosh! What am I supposed to do?
Astaga! Apa yang harus kulakukan?
What's gotten into you? You never come to my house.
Ada apa denganmu? Kau tak pernah ke rumahku.
Why didn't you answer your phone? I kept calling you last night.
Kenapa tak menjawab teleponmu? Aku meneleponmu semalam.
Do you know a lowly deity who has lived as long as the High Priest?
Kau kenal dewa rendahan yang seumuran Pendeta Agung?
As long as the High Priest?
Seumuran Pendeta Agung?
-Yes, there is one. -Who?
Ya, ada satu.
You know him too.
Kau kenal dia juga.
My gosh.
Astaga.
You're going overboard.
Kau berlebihan.
Hey, stop putting on an act. There's no one else but us.
Hei, berhenti berpura-pura. Tidak ada orang lain selain kita.
I saw the news a couple of days ago.
Kulihat beritanya beberapa hari lalu.
-It was you, wasn't it? -What are you talking about?
- Itu kau, 'kan? - Apa maksudmu?
An employee at a department store stopped an old lady from parking
Pegawai swalayan menghentikan wanita tua parkir di tempat difabel.
Then she got furious and slapped the employee
Lalu dia marah dan menampar pegawai itu
for not recognizing a VIP customer.
karena tak mengenali pelanggan VVIP.
I was just trying to educate a dumb human being.
Aku hanya mencoba mendidik manusia bodoh. Entah kenapa semua jadi marah.
It's getting harder to live here these days.
Makin sulit tinggal di sini.
Hey, Eunuch Kim!
Hei, Kasim Kim!
-Long time no see. -Don't call me "Eunuch."
- Lama tak jumpa. - Jangan panggil "Kasim".
-Can't you see this badge? -My gosh, what a nice car.
Lihat lencana ini?
All your life, you learned how to steal.
Seumur hidup kau belajar mencuri.
300 years ago, you were in and out of prison.
Tiga ratus tahun lalu, kau keluar masuk penjara.
I guess what you learned back then is finally working to your advantage.
Kurasa yang kau pelajari saat itu akhirnya menguntungkanmu.
Do you know how much I suffered
Apa kau tahu betapa aku menderita
because you told on me to a human king back then?
karena kau minta aku jadi raja manusia saat itu?
You mannerless jerk.
Dasar tak tahu sopan santun.
We're both lowly. Let's stop talking about manners.
Kita rendahan. Jangan bahas tata krama.
Do you have any good news?
Apa ada kabar baik?
I'll take anything regarding politics, society,
Beri tahu aku soal politik, sosial,
economics, and entertainment. Let's help each other out here.
ekonomi, dan hiburan.
-I don't know. -My gosh!
- Entahlah. - Astaga.
Jingeon. I haven't seen him in so long.
Jingeon. Aku sudah lama tak melihatnya.
Have you ever heard his voice before?
Pernah dengar suaranya?
Can he talk?
Dia bisa bicara?
Our hero.
Pahlawan kita.
Jugeollin the Scaredy-cat is also here.
Jugeollin si Kucing Penakut di sini juga.
-Lord Judong has disappeared? -Yes.
- Tuan Judong menghilang? - Ya.
They want us to find him when they can't even find him themselves.
Mereka mau kita mencarinya padahal mereka sendiri tak bisa.
I was looking forward to not seeing any of those gods in this world.
Aku tak mau melihat para dewa itu di dunia ini.
I guess that's why Habaek is still here.
Kurasa itu sebabnya Habaek masih di sini.
Jugeollin, you're our one and only hero.
Jugeollin, kau satu-satunya pahlawan kita.
He's right.
Dia benar.
You're the only one who scarred Habaek's face and ran away.
Hanya kau yang mencakar wajah Habaek dan kabur.
My gosh, how can you say that about our future king?
Astaga, kenapa bicara begitu soal calon raja kita?
What?
Apa?
Why are you scared?
Kenapa takut?
He may be a king there, but he's nothing here.
Dia mungkin raja di sana, tapi di sini bukan.
Why do you think we're staying in this pathetic world of humans?
Menurutmu kenapa kita tinggal di dunia manusia menyedihkan ini?
If I see him right now...
Jika kulihat dia sekarang…
-I don't know. -My gosh! I'm going!
Aku tak tahu.
Okay.
Baik.
My gosh. I've never seen a pack of criminals meet for breakfast.
Astaga.
What are you doing at this hour?
Sedang apa kalian?
You can't even come up with anything in broad daylight.
Kau bahkan tak bisa temukan apa pun di siang bolong.
I'll go now.
Aku pamit dulu.
I don't know. Let's go.
Entahlah. Ayo pergi.
I don't know.
Aku tak tahu.
You can't go yet. Wait here.
Kau jangan pergi dulu.
My gosh, why is Mura here?
Astaga, kenapa Mura di sini?
I don't know. They're seriously killing me.
Aku tak tahu. Mereka serius ingin membunuhku.
Lady Mura, I...
Nyonya Mura, aku...
How dare you
Berani sekali kau
scar Habaek's face and run away?
melukai wajah Habaek dan kabur?
I only ran away
Aku hanya melarikan diri
because you were threatening to kill me back then.
karena kau mengancam akan membunuhku saat itu.
I really didn't say anything to Lord Habaek.
Aku sungguh tak mengatakan apa pun kepada Tuan Habaek.
I didn't tell him anything about who made me challenge him.
Aku tak bilang apa-apa tentang siapa yang menyuruhku
Shut that mouth.
Tutup mulutmu.
Yes, of course.
Ya, tentu saja.
I didn't tell him it was you who told me to challenge--
Aku tak bilang kaulah yang menyuruhku...
-I told you to shut it. -Yes, okay.
- Tutup mulutmu! - Ya, baiklah.
You told me to beat Habaek until--
Kau menyuruhku memukuli Habaek sampai...
Shut it! Just shut that mouth!
Diam. Tutup mulut saja!
Shut it if you don't want me to crush your tongue.
Diam jika tak ingin kuremukkan lidahmu.
If you want me to spare your life in this world, shut your mouth!
Jika kau mau kubiarkan hidup di dunia ini, tutup mulut!
Yes, I will shut my mouth.
Ya, aku akan tutup mulut.
Are you guys shooting a comedy show?
Apa kalian syuting acara komedi?
What's so funny?
Apa yang lucu?
You both are like you're from Dumb and Dumber.
Kalian berdua seperti tokoh Dumb and Dumber.
Rather than Habaek finding out,
Daripada Habaek tahu,
you're more scared that he'll find out that you were jealous.
kau lebih takut dia tahu kau cemburu.
That challenge incident happened
Insiden tantangan itu terjadi
when the woman named Shim got sold for 300 packs of rice.
saat wanita bernama Shim dijual seharga 300 bungkus beras.
Am I correct?
Apa aku benar?
You were mistaken.
Kau salah.
Habaek didn't like her either.
Habaek juga tak menyukainya.
You were just too blind to see that.
Kau terlalu buta untuk melihatnya.
Hey,
Hei...
just tell him how you feel.
ungkapkan saja perasaanmu.
It's much better to get rejected face-to-face.
Lebih baik ditolak secara langsung.
Why do you care?
Kenapa kau peduli?
I just can't stand to watch you be like this. That's why.
Aku tak tahan melihatmu begini.
You're a goddess. You can't be this pathetic.
Kau seorang dewi. Jangan menyedihkan.
Hey, take me with you. What's going on?
Hei, aku ikut. Ada apa?
Hey.
Hei.
Does everyone hate me?
Apa semua orang membenciku?
-It's expensive. Do you like it? -Not really.
- Itu mahal. Kau suka? - Tidak juga.
Eat up. We always need to prepare ourselves.
Makanlah. Kita harus berjaga-jaga.
What would Jugeollin know about that stone?
Apa yang ingin Jugeollin tahu soal batu itu?
The High Priest once told me something.
Pendeta Agung pernah memberitahuku sesuatu.
I didn't put much meaning into it back then.
Kala itu, aku tak begitu peduli.
But if he's lived as long as the High Priest,
Tapi jika dia seumuran Pendeta Agung, dia mungkin tahu sesuatu.
-What did the High Priest say? -Do you know... the story about that guy?
- Apa kata Pendeta Agung? - Kau tahu
I brought him here.
Aku membawanya.
My gosh.
Astaga.
Lord Habaek.
Tuan Habaek.
Please kill...
Tolong bunuh...
No. Please have mercy.
Tidak. Ampuni aku.
No, just kill...
Tidak, bunuh saja…
I must have lost my mind back then.
Aku pasti sudah gila saat itu.
Shut that mouth of yours.
Tutup mulut kotormu!
Listen to me carefully. We're going to ask you a few questions.
Dengarkan baik-baik. Kami mau bertanya padamu.
If you answer them, we'll set you free.
Jika kau jawab, akan kami bebaskan.
But if you say anything to anyone,
Tapi jika kau katakan sesuatu pada siapa pun
I'm going to freeze and break
aku akan membekukan
that flapping tongue of yours.
dan menghancurkan lidahmu itu.
Do you know a lowly deity named Jingeon? Do you know why he can't talk?
Kau kenal dewa rendahan bernama Jingeon?
What is this?
Apa ini?
I brought this stone from the Divine Gate. It has the bloodstain of a human being.
Kubawa batu ini dari Gerbang Surgawi.
Oh, is that so?
Begitukah?
What?
Apa?
That can't be.
- Mustahil. Gerbang Surgawi tak bisa... - Aku tahu.
In what circumstance can this be possible?
Dalam situasi apa ini bisa terjadi?
There's no way that this can happen.
Tak mungkin ini bisa terjadi.
Let me rephrase that.
Biar kuubah kalimatnya.
Who can make this...
Siapa yang bisa
possible?
melakukan ini?
No one can make this possible...
Tak ada yang bisa melakukan ini…
No way!
Tidak mungkin.
This is not possible.
Ini mustahil.
What are you saying? Tell us what you mean.
Apa maksudmu? Katakan yang kau tahu.
If this is really the blood of a human being,
Jika ini sungguh darah manusia,
it should've disappeared
harusnya hilang sebab memang begitulah yang seharusnya.
But if this blood does not disappear with the power of that land,
Tapi jika darah ini tak hilang karena kekuatan tanah itu,
that means it's him.
maka artinya ini darahnya.
What are you saying? Who are you talking about?
Apa maksudmu? Siapa yang kau bicarakan?
That's right. Him.
Benar. Dia.
You also think it's him, right?
- Kau juga pikir itu dia, 'kan? - Kalian ini...
No way.
Tidak mungkin.
Can you also tell me what you're all talking about?
Bisakah jelaskan apa yang kalian bicarakan?
But there's no way that he could be here.
Tapi tidak mungkin dia di sini.
I'm just saying that because nobody has ever seen him before.
Aku berkata begitu karena belum pernah ada yang melihatnya.
I'm just saying that he can't be here.
Aku hanya bilang mustahil dia di sini.
Biryeom always talks about him too.
Biryeom selalu membicarakannya juga.
You both could spend the whole night talking about him.
Kalian berdua bisa habiskan semalaman membicarakannya.
What is this about?
Ini soal apa?
I'm pretty sure Jugeollin is right.
Aku yakin Jugeollin benar.
I believed it when the High Priest told me about it.
Aku percaya saat Pendeta Agung memberitahuku.
But after I gave it some thought, it made no sense at all.
Tapi setelah kupikir, itu tak masuk akal.
What are you talking about?
Apa maksudmu?
But then why did the High Priest say that to me?
Lalu kenapa Pendeta Agung mengatakan itu kepadaku?
-What did he say? -What are you talking about?
- Apa katanya? - Apa maksudmu?
You guys are having a late meal.
Kalian sedang makan.
He's my friend.
Dia temanku.
You saw him yesterday.
Kau lihat dia kemarin.
He's Shin Hu-ye, the owner of this hotel.
Dia Shin Hu-ye, pemilik hotel ini.
We saw you by coincidence last night. You were with a woman we know.
Kami melihatmu semalam.
Are you the patient that was with Ms. Yun last time?
Apa kau pasien yang bersama Nona Yun tempo hari?
I guess I jumped to conclusions. Let me apologize.
Kurasa aku keliru.
He's not very social. Please be understanding.
Dia tak suka bergaul. Mohon pengertiannya.
No, it's okay. I'm the one who offended him first.
Tak apa-apa. Aku yang menyinggungnya lebih dulu.
Then please enjoy your meal.
Selamat menikmati makananmu.
I would've definitely fallen for him if I were human.
Aku pasti akan jatuh cinta padanya jika aku manusia.
He's too good for the servant,
Dia terlalu bagus untuk si pelayan,
but we should wish them both the best of luck.
tapi kita doakan mereka beruntung.
Where were we?
Sampai di mana tadi?
Yes, the High Priest. What did he say to you?
Ya, Pendeta Agung. Apa yang dia katakan?
Ms. Yun.
Nona Yun?
Ms. Descendant.
Nona Keturunan.
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa di sini?
Well, the thing is...
Begini...
I came here to meet someone.
aku datang untuk menemui seseorang.
Did you meet someone?
Kau ada janji juga?
What?
Apa?
No, never mind.
Tidak, lupakan saja.
-Ms. Yun. -Yes?
- Nona Yun. - Ya?
You're restless, and you're not making any sense.
Kau gelisah dan meracau.
If you act like this, I might mistakenly think that
Jika kau bersikap seperti ini, aku bisa keliru sebab
you changed your mind overnight.
berpikir kau berubah pikiran.
I got rejected, right?
Aku ditolak, ya?
Pardon?
Apa?
I guess she really must be in a good relationship with that rich guy.
Kurasa dia pasti menjalin hubungan baik dengan pria kaya itu.
I've never seen him smile like that.
Belum pernah kulihat dia tersenyum begitu.
Habaek.
Habaek.
Mr. Shin, follow me.
Pak Shin, ikuti aku.
Excuse me.
Permisi.
I got you.
Kena kau.
You just got caught.
Kau tertangkap basah.
-Did you know about him? -It's impossible.
- Kau sudah tahu tentangnya? - Mustahil.
-This guy's identity. -His identity?
Identitas pria ini.
Yun So-a.
Yun So-a.
Just like we suspect So-a because she is with him.
Seperti kita mencurigai So-a karena bersamanya.
Is that the kind of relationship you have with the CEO of the resort?
Apa hubunganmu dengan CEO resor?
Wouldn't he become curious about her because she is with you?
Bukankah dia akan penasaran soal So-a?
How about we come home together tomorrow since we didn't get to do it today?
Maukah pulang bersama besok
How does she know who they are?
Bagaimana dia tahu siapa mereka?
Reveal who you really are.
Ungkapkan jati dirimu.
He's stronger than Lord Habaek?
Lebih kuat dari Tuan Habaek?
I guess they did not warn you about my powers.
Kurasa mereka tak memperingatkanmu tentang kekuatanku.
That power of yours...
Kekuatanmu itu...
Habaek!
Habaek!
I said stop!
Kubilang, hentikan!